all right it is July 8th 2024 and it is
active inference insights number 24 a
reverse Insight so welcome Darius how
are you doing very well I apologize
everyone say for my stupid headband I'm
currently in El Salvador um and it's
very warm and my hair is everywhere so
I've just I've decided to strap it in so
um it's a bit of it's a bit of a look
I'm very well how are you Daniel good
well as we just briefly
discussed this is sort of the season
finale slash pivot point or next jump
and we will discuss some of the
Inception and journey of insight series
The 1 through 23 main episodes what is
next for insights what is next for you
and just however long that is so let us
begin with Y insights how did it come to
be and what were the beginning steps
like well first it's annoying that we
never made this to 25 you know it would
be nice to have a nice square number but
24 will do that's life I guess um how's
it come back well firstly thanks to your
generosity um in many ways and the
institute's generosity so I'm very
grateful for that um i' had done
podcasting with of University a little
bit after but I think I just noticed
there was there was a sort of Gap at
least in the institute's offerings uh
the live streams not like this one but
the other ones can be quite Technical
and I don't think necessarily offer a
way in and a way to see how active
inference exists in the sort of context
of theories of biology or Neuroscience
or philosophy or whatnot so there was a
space there I thought
and I just I guess I guess it was also
this idea that it was a way for people
to learn alongside me um and I think
that's always quite an efficient and
effective way of
podcasting uh because I don't you know
there's one thing that where people know
nothing and it's very difficult to have
a conversation with an expert and
there's another where there two experts
speaking and it's inaccessible for the
audience so was um I think we hopefully
found a kind of sweet spot where I was
sufficiently knowledgeable albeit to a
quite limited degree at the beginning
I'd say uh but enough that I could ask
insightful questions and be curious the
way it came about really was I did my
masters at UCL in 202 from 2022 to 2023
and about halfway through I sort of
discovered active inference probably
through predictive processing because
obviously Carl is at UCL and it's a big
Hub fact of inference although I think
there's an interesting relationship
between active inference in UCL because
not everyone's necessarily on board and
then I started attending I got on the
Discord so Miles who we just mentioned
before miles Taft was my supervisor at
UCL was also and is also interested in
active inflence and he recommended the
Discord and the The Institute so I
started doing that started attending the
textbook groups and then I think I just
messaged you um when would that being s
September October and it all came
together quite nicely and rather quickly
and then then again just people to thank
Carl really first and foremost to be the
first guest um a good three hours with
Carl was like very nerve-wracking
experience but I think a pretty you know
throw yourself in the deep end and then
I think hopefully it's just gone from
strength to strength um and I'm sure we
can sort of talk about how it's
evolved one thing about that certainly
by view count which is not everything
the most popular videos on our Channel
over the last year have have been
basically Chris fields's 2023 physics'
information processing and your series
and now I'm kind of reflecting on that
and uh when we have a presentation like
a guest stream that can get technical or
a live stream with a paper Focus there
are people there it's human however it's
also like a conversation with literature
and literature in conversation with
other topics whereas in Chris fields's
case with the course like format that's
a uh similar to a professor to audience
and then what you kind of brought into
play was like also the person to person
and so that sort of like direct human
element of the
conversation which is much more like a
textbook group but of course a textbook
group still has the textbook group as
reference point but once you kind of um
swim away from the wall of any text then
there's this like wide space of what you
can ask people and and like how you
prepared for sure and I think people
naturally are attracted to the kind of
uh you know what John Bal di Loos um
this kind of mutual dialectical
unfolding where I don't know we're both
we're both um affording each other the
opportunities for insights and one thing
I always sort of wanted to do and never
got around to doing was doing in-person
insights episodes um there was the
possibility of doing that I mean I think
the more it can be inod the more it can
be enacted the more it can be situated
the better and maybe that's the kind of
idea going forward I mean I I recognize
also that one of the benefits of The
Institute is it's kind of its location
is everywhere and nowhere it's this
distributed map and that's really
amazing because I think what you see on
the Institute is all these people coming
from completely different parts of the
world with completely different
interests and um being unified over this
one over an interest in this framework
at the same time I think yeah hopefully
what what what what sort of developed
was this kind of mutual unfolding and I
think that can really only be done be
done in dialogue I think you have to be
quite an exceptional speaker an orator
to be able to do that just through
through
monologue yeah wow interesting point
there okay so Carl and then dot dot dot
dot dot so yeah do any come to mind like
what was sort of a um a leadup or a
followup that was surprising or you know
without naming innocent how how did
people differ and how they approach like
what you ask and did well look everyone
to be honest everyone was really amazing
I mean for me just like being a pre-doc
but being like to have the that
generosity of people to give me their
time and actually re and take it
seriously and not give uh you know
flippant or or or oversimplified answers
was really something and I think I
recognized that with call when I asked
him about active influence he gave me a
sort 15 minute answer which basically
maths and I thought okay well this is
not going to be this is not going to be
a soft launch um so everyone sort of
unified has taken it really seriously
and been really engaged and that was
amazing I think there were a couple
Pinch Me moments um so one like I've
always loved John fi um really since
discovering Awakening from the meaning
crisis probably when I was about 17 or
18 he's always been a massive figure in
my life and I was lucky to meet him last
year and to be able to speak to him was
a really bizarre and special moment so
yeah John was really amazing I think
also there were some people who I think
what was nice about the process was
integrating some people who weren't
necessarily active influence per se but
still had insights from different
disciplines and different domains which
could bear on act inflence so I really
enjoy speaking to Mar and
stendera um about haiger because this
kind of notion of us being being
directed ultimately towards a Futurity I
think is very ining with active
inference in this emphasis on expected
free energy but everyone's been yeah
everyone's been a total Delight I think
also what's been really fun is having
like the debate was really fun um about
the markco blanket trick and I think
that's another thing to say I really
enjoyed having people who weren't
necessarily not only people from
different domains but also people who
weren't necessarily in the camp of
active inference so whether that was you
know a crystal leer for example just
being able to probe the relevant
questions I think is really important
because the the the framework is always
evolving and it's always important in my
opinion at least to have these not
necessarily outside voices but concerned
voices just to
temper uh proceedings and I guess you
had that when you know you've done live
streams with people like Mel Andrews um
so I think you know if this something
like this continues it's important that
we break out and listen to other voices
who might have something to
say awesome thank you yeah well about
the sort of contents what were some
topical
themes whether ones that developed like
even over those
months or just some emergent themes or
like what topics did you find coming up
or developing yeah so I think so I'm not
by training a philosopher of Science and
so I guess when I discovered that to
inference this whole notion of the map
and the territory was not Forefront in
my mind um and in many ways my
enthusiasm fact of inference I think has
been quite efficiently and importantly
mitigated or mitigated but just
constrained by that conversation so to
what degree can the maths actually
really tell you tell us anything about
lived well one lived experience two
human behavior and three like what the
brain is actually doing
or the brain or the body what they're
actually doing so that was a recurrent
conversation that kept coming up over
and over again uh this map territory or
map territory um and I think hopefully
it's been a contributor contributor to
this wider conversation that I know is
happening within active inference and
The Wider Community again about what
active inference can really say I tended
a talk by to Schick last week about well
I think it was predictive processing
flirt with transcendental idealism but
the conversation turned into a kind of
map territory thing and I think a lot
you know
now and even people coming into active
influences a new field are very much
aware of the importance of that
conversation so that was one thing that
I think was really really helpful the
other thing that always kept coming out
was Consciousness um and the lived
experience and I think that's in part
because that's really what my um
research focuses on and so people may
have noticed that the podcast was slowly
transforming into a podcast on
Consciousness but so be it
um and in that case I think all that was
cemented was the fact that I don't think
we know very much at all um so I mean
that in terms of the metaphysical
question really the hard problem and
then I guess on the flip side of that is
the importance of taking lived
experience very seriously and in my
opinion always kind of starting with the
phenomena doing the intricate and
careful phenomenological analysis of the
of the actual phenomenon in question
before applying your models or running
your experiments and so on so yeah the
map territory
Consciousness
um and and and much more and much much
more and I think also just active
influences plays in the history of ideas
um whether you are coming from a kind of
computational stance you're thinking
about hel HS machines or Jeffrey Hinton
or its relationship to neuron Nets or
whatever or whether you're a
phenomenologist or whether you're an
analytic philosopher of mind like Thomas
metzinger
just recognizing that the history and
the future is has come and will come
after us and it's I guess always
important to think about our place
within that that that stream of
time nice but there was much more there
was much more oh yes I'll definitely
look forward to not just Rel listening
but also to jointly analyzing the core
entities and the active inference
ontology okay two questions one and two
take as long as you want one what is
active inference two why is it important
to have insights about active
inference so I think my wife I might
have just put it there but what's the
first question what is AC of inference
and the second one why does it matter to
have
insights yeah so active inference is as
we all say the coroller of the free
energy principle it's um it's not the
same as predictive processing and I
think that's an important um Proviso
although a lot of people conflate the
two so the free energy principle
um tells you in terms of
mathematics uh that a organism or an
entity that persists over time can
always be described as if it is
minimizing this upper bound on surprise
that we call variational free energy um
and then act of inference I've always I
I I think to be fair there's an
interesting meta question here about
exactly what we are talking about when
we're talking about active inference but
I've always thought of that as the
process Theory associated with free
energy minimization now
this as if or can be described as the is
the kind of Paramount thing here um
because yes indeed there's a
mathematical way that you could start
from like a [ __ ] plank equation or or
or any sort of
um start from your Theory of physics
which is that it's a um it's a whatever
it is you know you have you have your
mathematical equation and
then you you say okay well therefore
given this we can cast self organization
as this minimization of variational free
energy the question is okay well we make
the axiomatic assumption that things do
persist over time so that's that's
relevant um but then the question really
is okay given that things are persisting
over time and given that they can like
that is a really nice Launchpad how are
things actually doing that and then I
guess this is the overlap with things
like autop paresis and in activism and
cybernetics and all of this stuff why is
it relevant to study AC well I think
because we we have to take seriously the
notion that things are self
organizing um it's not a trivial fact
right this is I think Schrodinger's big
Insight um back in the 50s which was
that life is a quite miraculous
phenomenon it is this neg entropic
phenomenon that seems to defy the second
law of
Thermodynamics um or at least offer a
quite interesting coun example to this
and there I know again this is not
necessarily my field of expertise but I
know there's a broad domain of thinking
why that happens in the first place I
mean why are these pockets of neg entr
entropy in the universe anyway um and
this obviously can take you all the way
to stuff like arguments from design um
all the way back down to like the role
of lived experience so I think it's very
important to study
self-organization
and but that said
it's important to realize that the
mathematics won't take you all the way
there so for me I've always viewed AC of
inference in the frage principle as a
very interesting
Launchpad but always with the
recognition that the answer I don't
think is is it can't be in the
mathematics is the mathematics at least
the way that I've of always viewed it or
or come to view it is an instrumental
Tool uh a very insightful instrumental
tool but not as we say the territory
itself
and I know Maxwell who I just chatted
with a couple of days ago he's just
released this preprint with dton and
Carl and they make very explicitly that
point so I think the next steps in
active inference is going to be
something like so what is so what is the
point right like you have the math and
it's this really interesting descripted
tool but then what and is it is it
really how secluded is it from what the
brain is doing because I think we forget
that within the whole Act of inference
ecosystem although it's different you do
get these ideas coming in like
predictive processing or predictive
coding or discret St space PDP work and
that's much more of a process theory
about it actually what is the brain
doing and then you know within those
theories you start having the
integration of stuff like active
inference oh oh sorry variational free
energy and expected free energy so for
me active inference is really
interesting because one thing seems to
be true which is that we are self
organizing and self-maintaining and
self-d
distinguishing I think the real work
needs to be done on
saying what is the instrumental tool
what is actually happening in a realist
Manner and where are the where are the
where how do we get from one to the
other and obviously this has been the
Paramount question throughout but I
think it's high time that someone comes
in and really
asks the the the sort of the path it's
like a generative passage but for the
for the science
real active inference has never been
tried well well well yeah well it was a
stochastic differential equation which
was which was escaping my uh attention
um what
that very interesting account
um impresses on me is you started with
the downstream relationship of active
inference to free energy principles so
that's the high road yeah and in that
sense there's a grounding in general
thingness particular partition more like
a systems theory then you said that's a
Launchpad to get down to the meeting
point because you get that surprisal
minimization VF from the top and then
with all of these existing basian
architectures as various low road paths
those also have kind of convergently
described the evidence lower bounds
multiple
V
ising it's actually coming from the low
road methodologically but it's as if
it's coming from the high road so that's
one place they meet then you said well
that is like that's like another
orthagonal
Launchpad for people who want to do
something other than
develop that infrastructure which will
remain its own research program and
Direction and everything but then it's
going to be that's so what so what okay
so we have RX INF fur with the dragon
drop and everything works fine and here
and then what so that's that's very
interesting and anticipatory I think I
think just think first and foremost
always for anyone coming in just
recognizing that these things don't all
mean the same thing the free energy
principle does not mean predictive
processing predictive processing does
not mean a you know it doesn't
necessarily rely on an upper bound on
surprisal and so on and so forth and so
I think I think all credit to P Petula
and friston for sketching this out quite
effectively in their textbook and also
the way that you guys teach this in in
the textbook group and then also the the
resources of The
Institute I don't you know it's
important I think I mean there are lots
of Twitter debates that rage about how
ignorant the active influence Community
is interestingly within the kind of
ecosystem they're not uh and they're
very I I personally think they're very
humble and aware of the of the
limitations so yeah so so I don't know
what the ultimate solution and the
symphasis is whether there is such a
thing um but I think it's it's it's a
kind of we got to start with the
multiplicity before looking at the unity
and then trying to see if there's un
unity in the multiplicity which is sort
of both Mill Christ and he and all
together you know and alluded to in the
neat and Scruffy also early in the
textbook um okay so that that that's
very interesting um so several paths
ahead yes first how about some of your
own directions and then we'll talk more
about like where it could insights go
sure so I'm starting my PhD in
October in at mcari in Sydney so I'm my
supervisor in Nez poito and Raphael Mia
and I'm very very excited and very
grateful to have the opportunity uh and
moving to the other side of the world as
well which is I will be I am on the
other side of the world right now but
you know actually setting up residence
it's slightly scary but it's exciting
nevertheless um and I want to explore
principally
subjectivity and the sense of self as
well as what if like what a self is um
so this some of this is foreshadowed in
the work that we did on Flow State
so this was uh me L KL Ry jaob and Miles
TFT and I think there what became really
Paramount to me was that the notion of
self almost like the notion of active
inference becomes conflated and confused
because people don't make it clear where
they're talking about the metaphysical
self as if there is a sort of cartian
ego or a sense of self even when they're
talking about sense of self they're not
distinguishing between a a self as
subject and a self or a sense of self as
subject and the sense of self as object
so I I'm really interested in
subjectivity the fact that experience
seems to have a certain for meanus and
there's an ongoing debate about the
degree to which that's a universal
condition of Consciousness so this is
people like Anica but really going all
the way back to Dan Harvey and um Joseph
haras and Louis SAS all the way you know
back into the '90s and I think linking
all that together as well is an interest
in being being in the world in the
hiigaran sense and skillful coping in
the sort of Dr fussy and Merlo Ponte
sense so seeing if there's interesting
connections between subjectivity and
this familiar coping that we have in the
world so that's a couple of strands and
then I think naturally from that one
becomes embroiled in what is being in
the world to what degree does it um
involve representations there was just
this big paper that came out led by
Johannes Jer on the fact that relevance
realization and agency and cognition
therefore can't be computational so for
me I read that and I think it's very
Merlo ponan and very dra foran um and so
those are the big philosophers that kind
of inform my thinking on this front so
just seeing I mean it's all quite open
but I think hopefully there's a kind of
cluster there that's emerging because
there is also a more meta question about
the degree which we could
computationally model something like
subjectivity if the fundamental aspects
of cognition aren't computational
algorithmic and representational and I
think it's a fair presumption that
subjectivity might not be so this is a
big mystery basically that no one knows
where any of where the four meus comes
from and first and foremost no one
really necessarily knows what the four
meus is so some people take almost
without critical analysis that the for
meanus is because there is self a
homunculus located behind the Eyes For
Whom experience is given I think it's
quite clear that that isn't the case
from the human analysis from the
neuroscientific analysis so there's
really nice work by people like Kenneth
willford um and going all the way back
to Aaron goit and SRA about the fact
that Consciousness might be the the
subject relas of Consciousness might be
Consciousness itself so it's exploring
this kind of thing and
then I then I guess for me as well
something that's really important is
collaboration um I've been really really
really really lucky to be coll to have
collaborated already with really amazing
people um not only the people on the
flow paper but also people like Libby s
on the piece we did on tourettes and
self modeling so really just trying to
get integrated into this community this
philosophical this um theoretical
biological community as much as possible
and then seeing again what act of
influence can do for all of that so I
think not
necessarily making active inference the
front and
center because I not sure I don't think
I could without necessarily because of
all of the big meta scientific questions
that reside in active inference the map
territory thing so I think using it as a
tool and then if there are developments
either done by myself or other people
about a more biologically realist robust
theory of actually what the brain is
doing but absolutely fleshing that out
and trying to do this what Maxwell and
of called the generative passage tying
phenomenology or or the lived experience
to modeling to experimentation but
always always being aware of just how
fraught with danger or how precarious
and fragile that passage can be so
that's the idea at least it's quite
broad it will narrow down cool wow
well that's it's exciting to begin the
PhD um what you said about active
inference not being front and center for
some reason it made me think of like
famous or powerful photography or
documentation and it's like the map and
the methodology so that' be like the
open source methods
element however outside of the gear
enthusiasts connoisseur respector
development Community it'd be like okay
but what about the picture so so not
that that's a reductionist view on the
totality of like photography or anything
like that but just like it it may become
relevant for for a larger and larger
fraction to focus on how that picture
looks rather than um that's absolutely
right what the methods and the tools are
I think just I just think maybe because
of the way I'm
composed and maybe because my background
is ultimately in some in philosophy of
mind and
philosophy I I I I do think for myself
starting with the
phenomena is the first place never for
not not only never forgetting the
phenomena but starting with a phenomena
so I've just been writing this thing
about
attention and it's funny how strange the
notion of attention can
be once you lose sight of how it
actually phenomenologically unfolds and
and how it structures Consciousness so
for me and again this is not
disrespecting anyone who wants to start
with the modeling or wants to start with
the map
but I'm probably inclined to go the
other
way that makes me think about textbook
group it's like quite literally
sometimes circle square Line Circle
Square o s a b c d e and then it's like
well even if you were going to make a
map of your street and intersection
you'd be talking about like 20 to 100
circles and squares pulled up to the
level of abstraction of something like a
PDP and then that's like getting into
the multi-agent and all of these
Concepts yeah and then also made me
think of like what is this s obviously
great question to um to do the PHD in
and the immune system and the sensory
and the affector and all these different
self Concepts and then seeing what's
happening now with like agentic ai ai
agents defined in terms of like
perception and action which is like one
thingness and then at the same time as
as Maxwell also emphasized in the uh
Discord recently like the agentic focus
which is one system of Interest or genre
of system of Interest actually minimizes
the apparent scope because especially
grounded more in the high road of just
how things are as if they are rather
than any particularly built architecture
then it's like yeah
there's no reason why it should be kind
of an agentic boundary it could be like
an ecosystem of shared intelligence and
then that's where all these self
concepts are in like a kind of
Multiplicity almost by definition sure I
mean I I I guess I guess
ultimately we don't know um so so like
this notion of individuated s is is is
in many ways at least I've always taken
it to be an underlying axium of active
inference right I mean if one was to say
that well we're all just non-
individuated things in the soup then you
can't really apply the Mark or blanket
partition in the first place so it's a
healthy way to
start but even if you read I mean I was
just reading something yesterday on it
was like autopoetic autonomic and
activism um so just just it it was a
really interesting piece see if I can
find who wrote it it's a very it was
very good um but ultimately
and they were they were trying to do is
saying okay why is in activism why why
are there been these two strands for in
activism sensory motor in activism and
then autonomic based on basically
autopoetic in activism and trying to
kind of merge the two and saying okay
well what's at the heart of living might
be something like sensory motor and
activism but not discounting the fact
that there is this operational closure
within the system but again one has to
recognize there that like there's a
there's a kind of embedded circularity
which is that we already take the system
for granted so we're saying like what
what con what allows the system to
self-maintain whether it's operational
closure but thermodynamic
openness and then but what does that do
well it maintains the self-organization
and and allows for self-maintenance and
so there is and and this is obviously
recognized by those authors there is
this kind of inherent
circularity and this notion of like a
strange Loop has clearly always been
pointed to at the heart of of of well
intelligence and cognition so I think
also getting to the to the bottom of
that Circle which for many philosophers
would be problematic but actually for
these theorists is kind of at the very
heart of their theories is a really
interesting thing but yeah again not
forgetting that literally recognizing or
believing theoretically that there are
individuated things can look like an
axiomatic presupposition and in active
inference it almost certainly is one
so yeah I mean I mean what is a self
really is the big question I guess
there's there's really good Pap I always
do this it's like I'm in podcast mode
again but it's um verel I think it's
1991 it's called a meshwork of selfless
selves really good really really good
because again it's not saying that this
is a self in the sort of strict
cartisian way that we all might have a
focus psychology theory of but like some
of these are intuitive or viable ways
that we could Define the self whether
this is a sensory motor boundary a
Cellar boundary and so on and so forth
so yeah it's it's a surprisingly elusive
concept the
self yeah so much to say on that I mean
even if you apply a utilitarian or
pragmatist approach to your own agency
over an intentional profile over
self-concepts it would be like that's
the strangeness or part of the
strangeness and the second order
with the okay I'll read some comments
from the live chat and we'll keep
talking about this before we do
eventually talk about like where the
series go okay upcycle Club writes
greetings wave hand emoji I have really
enjoyed the insights active inference
series with Darius I wish you all the
best in your future endeavors well thank
you that's very kind I mean yeah thank
yeah go go go oh yeah thanks Up Cycle
all right Terry mold writes I've loved
the talks the latest one I really
thought the free energy principle could
resolve the different approaches if you
remove the idea of a pre-ordained agency
of the individual make
sense
um yeah I mean again depends on how you
define agency but um if you just Define
agency as the ability to again in like
the in activist tradition to set your
own norms and standards with respect to
your surrounding mure um then active INF
is very consonant with those ideas so
I'm not too sure whether you can really
dis uh you know discard the notion of
agency when you're talking about active
inference because at the very heart of
active inference is this sensory motor
contingency so again I think it slightly
depends on what one means by agency um
if I mean clearly there are things that
don't necessarily move and change the
world according to their internal norms
and by this I don't mean conscious norms
I mean the Norms that an eoli bacterion
would have and for those I guess at the
you know at the mark of blanket you just
leave the the active partition no but no
I mean I mean I don't think active
influence completely flens out this
distinction between agentic and non-
agentic systems um in many ways it might
reinforce this idea that agency is
active influence and active influence is
agency
so again always just a epistemic
humility I guess I don't know what AC I
don't know what the free energy
principle solves but I don't think it
it's going to be able to uh yeah discard
and dispense of agency so so sort of
Thoroughly okay Terry added like an
emotional valtion which I think gets
added after the event well what what I
think is interesting about this and
relates to your flow work and some of
the other discussions that have come up
about time is that
view from the inside and view from the
outside of potentially time scales that
are working in this integrated way where
there's this kind of like it's it's a
complex moment what is happening and
that's even before getting into like
different ways we can think about
SpaceTime so it's like in that rewriting
pre-writing now casting body integrating
Zone there's so much to explore and and
like you said about the map territory
earlier it's like good to go into a
complex
territory knowing what's a map and
what's the territory at least in kind
100% And so whenever you know we there
is a there is a PM DP in the float
States paper and in The Tourette's paper
but hopefully it's made pretty clear
that this is an
idealization um I was very lucky
actually as an undergrad to study
Chomsky in linguistics and the notion of
idealization comes up a lot in Chomsky
and so I think I was at least in that
sense quite well I know I said earlier
I'm not a philosopher of science but
there was some we had there there were
quite a few discussions about
idealization and science so yeah yeah in
those cases I mean God knows how
recursive and hierarchical these layers
are and I think in some cases all you
have to do is point at it and say you
know at this degree of complexity one
must remain silent there's an
interesting thing there about um emotion
coming after the um after the phenomenon
I'm not quite sure I agree I mean I have
flirted with the idea that for example
in flow states there is no consciousness
um or at least no emotion that there is
an ongoing discussion again I'm not I'm
not an emotion theorist but there's a I
believe it's within appraisal theory
about the fact that just if we take a
motion to be an appraisal of let's say
an inter receptive signal it doesn't
actually have to mean that this can only
be done offline it could be done in real
time and I think informed Again by
someone like draus or Merlo Ponte that's
that's quite right um the emotion in
many ways whether it's
now there's an interesting question here
is about actually what the causal role
of that emotion is because there are two
different things here one is its causal
role and one is its
temporal um status the interesting uh
causal role is whether that emotion
actually does anything for the organism
who's trying to return to this kind of
equilibrium or what um draus would call
your sort of optimal grip with the gal
so I don't know I I don't think the
flowing agent is non conscious I don't
think they're a robot um so no UL to
answer your question I don't think the
free energy principle solves everything
by dispensing with agency because one I
don't think it can answer the question
of agency two I don't think there's a
robust definition of agency within the
free energy principle literature or
elsewhere and and thirdly under certain
definitions agency is inbuilt within
actively inferring
agents I'm
note that I I'm using agents with speech
marks because when I talk about asan I'm
not talking about some cartisian
homunculus so big questions big
questions um which need lots of years of
deep delegation to to resolve cool okay
more to the operational closure yes so
having organized many many live streams
and worked with many people what was
very different about your co-organizing
was basically you did all the
invitation you recorded it and just
shared the upload so logistically what
did it take in terms of research
background prep confirmation all that
kind of stuff how would you evaluate
that and or how how would you we'll just
ask that question first just how was it
how was it and how you actually did it
well I I like doing this stuff so I love
emails um and maybe this is a betrayal
of my age and inexperience but I I love
sending emails so well you very kindly
had the spread we have a spreadsheet
which is going to be hidden from
everyone else but we have a of Coda
spreadsheet where we have just a list I
think there was there was a list of
people who had been on live streams
before and then maybe potential guests
and then we we did another one where it
was people and then there was a way of
sort of categorizing it people I'd
invited people I was thinking invited
people had been on so for me I mean the
one was recognizing it's an active
inference podcast so starting with the
kind of canonical figures
that said there were some canonical
figures who didn't appear on the show so
that might be we could talk about that
and who else could be there because
there were certainly people who I think
Were Meant to come on and then there
were logistical timing issues and and so
we can get to that but you know I think
for anyone listening who wants to do
something like this people are
unbelievably receptive and generous with
their time um so really ultimately it
was just a question of asking of course
there are ways of asking so I was always
you know one always has to be very
polite and considerate if people say no
which some people did then that's
totally fine um but really it was just a
question of asking so we use zenc caster
which is
a podcasting tool that only works on
Google Chrome and they've been really
good I mean what's nice about them is I
think they're a really small company and
so whenever I had sort of little issues
I would just ask them and they would get
back to me super quickly so shout out to
Zen caster and then I guess logistic
basically the only other thing was just
how big those files got so a warning I
mean people who do podcasts and live
streams will know I mean these were big
you know 24 25 gig things and so good
Wi-Fi and and an external hard drive
turned out to be useful but no it it's
it's gone quite smoothly I'd say it's
gone quite smoothly don't get me wrong
it's a learning process so Daniel you'll
know this there's a like one starts with
no I mean right now I'm just on my
laptop but people will probably be able
to notice the difference right I don't
have a light in front of my camera I
don't have a different camera I don't
have a uh microphone and so I think
there were it's an optimization thing
like active inference it's sort of going
okay I'm starting from here and I'm
accepting myself from starting here as
the complete Layman the novice and I
didn't really set myself a goal of where
I wented to end up but I just knew I
could get
better and I hope and people seem to
think that the quality of it has gone up
and up as time's gone on um but I think
there's still massive scope and it's
super cool that you guys now have
charity status and hopefully that sort
of raises the ceiling here and so yeah I
mean personally I'm just really excited
to see where this can go recognizing
also the podcast face is a little is a
little bit
saturated and so I think when we talk
about pushing this podcast forward
thinking about how we can be Innovative
um in setting up new schema for for
guests and and and live streams
throughout so yeah surprisingly quite
quite a sort of fluent and and not too
tricky
process how how would you see it
continuing like what would a very cool
volunteer or intern or research fellow
do or how how could they kind of jump in
and continue just thematically and from
the same like intention Center like what
do you see that as actually being like
for someone to do look I think
ultimately first and foremost I would
always just say speak to the people that
are you're interested in and this is a
sort of Trope I think in in podcasting
which is you know there's a vacuum going
on so I'm go hold on this is this is the
issue of doing this in in in El
Salvadorian host there's a lot of noise
everywhere um but I think ultimately
okay you know the audience is going to
be it's going to be quite evidence to
the audience if you're doing it for them
and I'm not saying disc discount the
interest of the audience but
I I loved everyone I spoke to so I think
whoever the research uh is the podcast
that is ensuring that they know who they
want to speak
to um is really important I think
preparation was really important now I
don't mean writing down all the
questions you don't do this I don't mean
writing down all the questions you're
going to ask I always really had about
three or four themes
and maybe in certain cases an actual
like well-formed question because it
might have been slightly recursive and
complicated but generally and I always
said this to guests before we went live
it's meant to be free
flowing so I think keeping that at least
for the podcast Space is really
important I think that
said could the community actually be
even more personal you know one of the
really nice things that you guys did was
the with Carl which I love I love I
think it's great and so I think even
little stuff like that could be really
nice additions to the process um
because well for many people the only
thing they see are their work and their
Twitter account so so kind of getting to
know people I think is is relevant and
then yeah I mean final thing I'll say
is don't I don't think we should Silo
ourselves in to only speak to people
that we agree with in speaking in this
case um and so constantly you know
whether that's people who have actually
been actively critical of active
inference in writing in the past so I
don't know Ezekiel dealo or Evan
Thompson or some like this or even
someone who you know might not just be a
even someone within the community right
like myself who is not dispensing with
the map territory distinction just
having that that dialect that dialectic
is really really important so yeah I
think there's plenty there I mean I'd
love I'd love to see it
continue um I would watch every episode
like an avid supporter um and yeah again
again I'm just super yeah I'd be very
happy to help out wherever I can but for
me personally and we spoke about this
it's kind of time to lock in I think um
I guess it's one of those things I mean
I don't know I'll ask you I think at
certain point to be totally candid I was
slightly worried that I was becoming a
podcaster and I guess for me what I want
from my academic life at least is to be
writing and reading and doing academic
work so I I'm curious about your
experience how much do you feel like the
stuff that you
do takes away time for writing reading
and doing the kind of canonical academic
activities that's a great question so
it's um there's a lot to say on it and
and uh of course what I can say about my
own last like 10 years doesn't apply
necessarily broadly but during graduate
school from 2014 to 2019 I was doing
multiple weeks plus of fieldwork in the
desert and while I was on Stanford
campus I was not taking video meetings I
was not like in the digital so during
graduate
school absolutely it makes sense to be
really focused and then one thing I
started exploring at the end of graduate
school was live streaming some over head
view hand drawing so with no audio so
that got me familiar with OBS The open-
Source broadcasting software and just
the
logistics of doing something that is
largely improvisational so not preparing
more than oh maybe here's a reference
image okay yeah so getting the time of
live streaming as close to real time
which is this kind of like Marshall
mccluhan angle on the whole thing plus
like people's feedback so that's like
one sort of Lane which even now doesn't
take much more time than like you
mentioned several emails and and the
time itself and then where it starts to
really be like okay this is like reading
the paper making the slides that the
question is how slash is that aligned
with like relevant learning and research
formats so like
the0 Style video um that kind of came
into play with just the pure background
and context before even if we had a
broader discussion on the paper that was
like almost exactly the lab meeting
slides which then during the second half
of the lab meeting we okay go back to
figure three or like what where was the
abstracts like being able to have
sections up there on the slide form and
have one person who could say like that
they had really fully gone through the
whole thing so again that's the
conversation with literature but from a
combination
of alignment of Education research
service interest and then the logistical
element of most streams not taking more
but then there is still that element of
just like what has happened um but you
know that's Dan but Daniel you're you're
you're a beast I mean like it's worth
saying you know I think everyone's very
grateful for the work you've done I mean
it's like there's nothing else like it
really so I mean not to be not to speak
out of turn but like well done like it's
really really something and I think also
like to say that this is the place to go
to learn about active inflence I I I
came to this you know I
didn't this The Institute is known and I
mean the the Discord is getting bigger
and bigger and so yeah it's really
remarkable um you know for me to be in
London with not even necessarily overt
active inference people and them going
oh well I know there's a textbook group
I know there's this chat I know that you
know Daniel is doing this and that is a
real sign of success um and so long may
it continue I guess but yeah I I think
something you said there was I forgot to
mention was all the paper reading so I I
hope this is quite obvious obviously one
has to know what who they're talking
to and so I think this in many ways
informs my thing about speak to people
you want to speak to now I'm quite lucky
because I basically love reading
academic
papers but me it's just a hobby right
like so it doesn't feel like work I love
reading books I love read academic
papers I was also really lucky and I
think this is just a logistical point
that I had institutional access
throughout and this is a broader
educational point which is that a lot of
people don't have access to papers if
they're not open access so
I think that is probably the majority of
the time goes into reading papers
reading the papers of the people you're
going to be speaking to and making sure
that the questions that you ask are
really tied to their work because
there's no point in me speaking to Ian
mcgilchrist about quantum mechanics
really um and so I mean I'm sure he'd
have something actually quite miraculous
to say but you know you get my point so
yeah I you know maybe this is something
that the Institute could also work on
finding a way for people to access
papers because for the vast majority of
people who don't have a edu they can
only see the
abstract um but yeah on the whole yeah
it's been it's been a really really
Splendid experience I I mean there are I
think there are plenty of people as well
that we could get on um who would have
lots to
say awesome yeah I think maybe we could
do something like see who's interested
you could ask a few people and the time
will be right when the time is right so
there's no right need to um to jump on
it I think to to ferment and digest with
like the 50 hours or whatever it is
there's a lot there's a lot there's a
lot there that people I hope will be
able to
glean maybe not even insights from but
just you know I think the role of
philosophy in many ways is is finding
the right questions to try and answer so
it's not necessarily always about
answering the questions it's about
structuring the
conversation and so hopefully we've
opened up that landscape where the
questions now are more concretized in
people's heads the relevant questions so
yeah yeah I mean I don't know hopefully
an interns watching I love this
internship thing that you guys are doing
as well um and they're interested in
taking it on because it's all theirs but
again as I say whoever's watching and
might be interested I am will be it
although on the other side of the world
right now in not the most Wi-Fi robust
Place although I have found some good
Wi-Fi um I'm always very happy to help
always very very happy to help cool we
will uh see and we'll explore it so
thank you Darius for the very unique
series thanks Daniel and and I also
again thank you for all your help and
blur and Ali and everyone who's part of
the institute there's like loads and
loads and loads of work that goes in
that people don't see
and obviously like they see my face um
but yeah you guys have been incredibly
helpful and generous of your time and so
I'm really genuinely super super
grateful thank you I think there's a
piece there about like the future of
content slash
attention and whether and where we would
really want a person like where I would
want to know what you thought and where
we'll be able to use synthetic method
methods to just like generate different
kinds of material that would flood and
potentially be in distinguishable or
even preferable in certain ways than
than the real conversations real
dialogos that people would have an
experience so I think that like it you
know the way that you kind of also help
frame it in that context is um is
awesome so thank you again well I don't
although just just final thing I'll say
on
that I think there's something very
special about two speaking to one
another um and I think I all I'll say is
without the appropriate embodiment the
appropriate social context the approach
enculturation and so on and so
forth to have genuinely the effect to
genuinely not just mimic but replicate
the effect that can happen when true
dialogos is happening within two you
know among two artificial bodies in this
case
I will I will I will just say that I'm
skeptical but in the meantime let the
humans
talk and I'm sorry for sweating it's 35
degrees here so invariably there will
there is this is this is not glamorous
there is sweat ah and more so thank you
Darius see you thanks Daniel see peace
bye